Finding Aid for the American Institute of Landscape Architects Records LSC.1297
UCLA Library Special Collections
American Institute of Landscape Architects records
circa 1954-1977
UCLA Library Special Collections
American Institute of Landscape Architects
LSC.1297
52.5 Linear Feet (105 boxes and 1 oversize box)
The American Institute of Landscape Architects (AILA) began as the Southern California Landscape Architects (SCLA) in 1954 after the appointment of the State Registration of California Landscape Architects Board by California Governor Goodwin Knight. The institute was renamed the California Institute of Landscape Architects (CILA) then incorporated as the AILA in 1957. AILA became a national and international group before merging with the American Society of Landscape Architects (ASLA) in 1982. The collection consists of newsletters, correspondence, business records, and membership lists assembled from various sources related to the American Institute of Landscape Architects (AILA).
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Donald Roberts, 1980-1984.
Gift of Robert Cardoza, 1986.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 994621853606533
Biography
The American Institute of Landscape Architects (AILA) began as the Southern California Landscape Architects (SCLA) in 1954 after the appointment of the State Registration of California Landscape Architects Board by California Governor Goodwin Knight; renamed the California Institute of Landscape Architects (CILA); incorporated as the AILA in 1957; AILA became a national and international group before merging with the American Society of Landscape Architects (ASLA) in 1982.
Biographical Narrative
According to American Institute of Landscape Architect histories, the organization was conceived in 1952. The real beginning was in 1954, after the State Registration of California Landscape Architects Board was appointed by Governor Goodwin Knight. The group termed itself Southern California Landscape Architects (SCLA), then California Institute of Landscape Architects (CILA), before incorporating in 1957 as the American Institute of Landscape Architects (AILA). The organization's objectives were to provide the `middle ground' where the designer, practitioner, landscape contractor, and landscape nurseryman as well as those with more formal training, could meet and discuss common problems and experiences leading to the enrichment of professional work done. AILA became a national and international group. Two other groups already existed: California Council of Landscape Architects (CCLA) and American Society of Landscape Architects (ASLA). AILA was given representation to CCLA, but withdrew after feeling rules were not being strictly adhered to. For many years there seems to have been a rivalry with ASLA, though with suggestions at various times for merging with ASLA. In 1982 a merger was accomplished, so that AILA no longer exists.
Records in this collection do not form an archive, but have been assembled from various sources, primarily through the offices of Donald Roberts, UCLA Lecturer in Art, Design, and Art History, AILA national fellow and officeholder, AILA Los Angeles chapter. There is some material pertaining to or from all of the organizations mentioned above. The largest group of working documents comes from Glen H. Hunt, AILA president 1975-76. All other items are miscellaneous, but give a picture of the concerns and working methods of the chapters and national organization. There is information on state licensing boards and AILA student award programs. In the early and middle 70s AILA concerned itself with environmental issues, so there is a small amount of material about those. There is some material about the issues involved in a merger with ASLA.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of newsletters, correspondence, business records, and membership lists assembled from various sources related to the American Institute of Landscape Architects (AILA). The the largest group of documents in the collection was from Glen H. Hunt, AILA president, 1975-76, and additional materials came from Donald Roberts, an AILA national fellow and officer as well as UCLA lecturer. Material in the collection relates to the AILA and its growth, and subjects covered include local AILA chapters, AILA organization on the national level, state licensing boards, and AILA student award programs. There is some documentation relating to the AILA's concern with environmental issues in the early and middle 1970s as well as material relating to the AILA's merger with the American Society of Landscape Architects (ASLA).
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Southern California Landscape Architects (SCLA) files.
American Institute of Landscape Architects (AILA) files.
American Society of Landscape Architects (ASLA) files.
Business records.; Online resources.; Landscape architecture -- Archives.; American Institute of Landscape Architects--Archives; American Society of Landscape Architects.
- California Council of Landscape Architects Correspondence and Working Papers, [Box 1]
  - CCLA Newsletters, [Box 2, folders 1-3]
  - California Association of Landscape Architects Working Papers and Newsletter, [Box 2, folders 4-7]
  - Southern California Landscape Architects Items, [Box 2, folders 8-9]
  - California Institute of Landscape Architects Working Papers, [Box 2, folders 10-12]
  - American Institute of Landscape Architects - Items Gathered for a History of the Organization, [Box 2, folders 13-16]
- AILA--Items Arranged Chronologically By Cataloger, [Box 3]
- Glen Hunt Working Papers, from his Offices with AILA, [Boxes 4-5]
- Chapter Items and Working Papers (Including Los Angeles Chapter); Chapter Newsletters, [Box 6]
- AILA Newsletters, [Boxes 7-8]
- AILA Rosters, [Box 9]
- California Council of Landscape Architects
  - Correspondence, Seemingly Executive secretaries' files. Includes some by-laws, minutes, etc. for this period., 1955-57. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-61. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Roster, (?)., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, rosters, minutes, etc. seemingly kept by Warren E. Lauesen, 1958-61. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agendas, aims, correspondence, etc., 1959-60. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, budgets, etc., Lauesen materials., 1959. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Draft, Code of professional practice. Also comments, including those by Warner L. Marsh, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, budgets, mailings, etc., 1960-62. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, financial statements, mailings, etc., 1961-62. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - By-laws, (?)., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- CCLA Conventions
  - 1st annual, the Ahwahnee, Yosemite. Announcement, program, clippings, etc., 1955. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 2nd annual, the Biltmore, Santa Barbara. Announcement, program, Biltmore brochures, etc., 1956. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 3rd annual, Mark Thomas' Inn, Monterey. Announcement, program, Monterey map, etc., 1957. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 4th annual, El Mirador Hotel, Palm Springs. Program, roster, Palm Springs items, etc., 1958. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Reference manual., 1958/59; 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 5th annual, Yosemite Lodge, Yosemite. Announcement, program outline, program, roster., 1959. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reference manual., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 6th annual, Mission Inn, Riverside. Program., 1960. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 7th annual, El Dorado Hotel, Sacramento. Program, roster, Board of directors minutes, etc., 1961. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- California Council of Landscape Architects Newsletters
  General note
  [Inclusive dates - a draft list of actual holdings is in the Collections File]
  - Councilnews. vol.2 no.6 (). vol.7 no.5 ()., July 25, 1958 December 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - California Councilor. vol.2 no.1 (). vol.4 no.3 ()., May 1972 June 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CCLA News. vol.5 no.1 ()., April 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, rosters, 1955-57. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Suggested schedule of compensation, November 1954. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mimeographed items, including Excerpts from Articles of incorporation, 1957. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - CALA News. vol.6 no.7 (). vol.9 no.5 ()., February 4, 1955 December 28, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    [Inclusive dates - draft list in Collections File]
- Southern California Landscape Architects
  - Proposed code, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - California State Board of Landscape Architects, roster of licentiates, December 1954. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- California Institute of Landscape Architects
  - Correspondence, minutes, rosters (of organizing members), 1954-55. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Articles of incorporation and by-laws. Correspondence about and copies of, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Roster, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- American Institute of Landscape Architects (beginning, with this name), 1957
  [Items kept or gathered for establishing a history of the organization, ca. 1954-1970]
  - Rosters, narrative histories, 1954-70. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - American Institute of Landscape Architects, history and purposes. Typescript, Lists of names, correspondence, 1959. 1970. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Rosters, notable events of organization, correspondence, 1973-74. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Lists of members with some biographical information (pertaining to involvement with organization), ca. 50 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- AILA
  [Items Filed Chronologically by Cataloger]
  - Photograph of Jack Evans and Keith Peck; letter, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Two convention photographs, late 1950s/early 60s. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Removed to Package 1 because of mold.
  - Letter, 1958. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters from ASLA, 1959-60. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, agendas, 1960-61. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Roster, by-laws correspondence, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Annual meeting, Notes, financial statements., 1961. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, correspondence, Seemingly executive secretary's files., 1960-61. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Printed by-laws. Special report to AILA from public relations consultant, 1961. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Roster correspondence (mimeographed forms), 1962. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Seemingly executive secretary's files., 1959-62. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes The Council story (typescript explaining controversy with and withdrawal from CCLA).
  - Budgets, financial statements, 1958-65. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Garden planners, 1967. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - ASLA concurrent membership, 1967-68. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1967. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - convention. Correspondence, agendas, programs, etc., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Landscape Architects Emergency Committee. Mimeographed newsletters, 1968. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Letter to David Wedgewood, 1968. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - International conference, Asilomar, Registration form, program, etc., 1968. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Metropolitan Water District information, 1960 and 1968. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - State Board of Landscape Architects law (California) with rules and regulations and directory, 1969. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Mimeographed memo from president about officers, etc., 1968/69 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Letter from Wedgewood, 1969. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Brochures for AILA's spring tour., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Letters to Wedgewood, 1970-71. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - travel program questionnaire., 1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - International conference. Program, hotel brochure., 1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Update to directory of landscape architects., 1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - tour brochure., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - ASLA/AILA amalgamation. Correspondence, 1977.; (photocopies). (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Sample AILA membership applications. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Sample (blank) AILA awards of merit. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Richard P. Gawne, Riverside, California AILA [name tag from convention?]. (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Items from Glen Hunt, AILA Officeholder
  - Public relations. Correspondence, reports, 1970. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Public relations. Correspondence, 1970. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cascade [Seattle] chapter AILA environmental activities, 1971. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Environmental materials from Richard and Dion Neutra, 1971-72. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Committee on Environment. Correspondence, notes, 1971. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1973. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report of Glen Hunt, 1st vice president, notes on AILA goals, etc., 1974-75. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1974-75. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with 1st vice president Patrick Gushue, 1974-75. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Gushue, April-August 1976. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Student members. Correspondence, Director's report, 1974-76. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, International student director William J. Drulias, March-April 1975. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, primarily photocopies of Hunt's letters sent after election as president, 1975. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Financial statements, 1971-74.; (photocopies). (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Letters from executive vice president F.J. MacDonald, March-December 1975. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, various state AILA chapters, primarily concerning registration practices, state boards, etc., 1975. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with chapters, Includes rosters, notes, etc., 1975-76. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with William H. Peterson, 1975-76. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with 2nd vice president Taro Yamegami, March-June 1976. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with treasurer Arthur M. Surosky, April-June 1976. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Carbons of outgoing letters, welcoming new members, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, notes, rosters of committees, 1976-77. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Stephen Schwartz, International secretary/President Los Angeles chapter/By-laws committee, Includes by-laws information., 1976. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Public relations committee correspondence, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Rosters, mailing lists, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - a series of files These seemingly were kept chronologically rather than by subject as were most previous files (folder 1 of 4)., mid-1976 to early 1977. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (folder 2 of 4)., 1976-77 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (folder 3 of 4)., 1976-77 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (folder 4 of 4)., 1976-77 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Board of directors' questionnaire. Sent by Hunt, a mimeographed form, with questions on goals, etc. These are returned copies (folder 1 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Returned questionnaires (folder 2 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 16)
- AILA - Chapters
  [Most begin with items designated CILA]
  - San Diego
    - Founding meeting attendance list, 1957-58. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - officers, 1957-59. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Meetings. Correspondence, minutes, 1957-61. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Northern California
    - Founding meeting attendance list. Also correspondence, 1956. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Meetings. Correspondence, minutes, 1959-62. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Canada
    - Vocational course announcement, 1960. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Los Angeles
    - Financial statements, 1957-60. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Board of directors - agendas, 1960-65. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Board of directors - minutes, 1960-65. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Board of directors - minutes, 1962-63. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - General meetings - minutes, 1962. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Secretary Howard Baumgarten's files, Correspondence, announcements, minutes., 1968-69. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Board minutes and financial statements, 1973-75. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous items, Letters, agendas, etc., 1966-74. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - unspecified (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Los Angeles chapter - host, 1962 AILA annual meeting
    - Correspondence, annotated roster, minutes, convention site brochures. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - unspecified (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Los Angeles chapter - sponsor, Landscape architects' seminar, Lake Arrowhead: announcements, reservation forms, programs.
    - Water, an element of the landscape, 1967. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Elements of environment., 1968. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Space-time motivation., 1969. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - The diametrics of ecology., 1970. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Chapter Newsletters
    - Northern [California] chapter CILA. Bulletin no.1 ()., January 23, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Eastern Canada chapter. Bulletin no.1 ( Newsletter 2-4 ()., May 19, 1965); August and Winter 1965, March 1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Los Angeles chapter. Bulletin, June 20, 1974-November 1977. (Box 6, Folder 22)
- [National] AILA [beginning CILA] bulletin. no.1 ()., July 15, 1955-June 1964
  - 1955-59. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1960. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1961. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - January-March 1962. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - April-September 1962. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1963. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1964-65. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1966. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 1967-68. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1969. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1970-71. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1972. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1973-77. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Other AILA Newsletters
  - V.I.P. Bulletin. no.3-4 ()., May 21, June 25 and October 27, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Forum [title varies] ()., May/June, August and September 1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - American Institute Of Landscape Architects Journal,, no.2 (), no.4 (), no.5 (), no.6 ()., Summer 1965 Spring 1966 Spring 1968 1969 July 1970 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    [Moved to Package 1 because of mold]
- AILA Brochures
  - Your Career as a Landscape Architect (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Planning to Build?, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Related Publication
  - Landscape, [inclusive dates]., 1965-70 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- AILA Rosters
  - 1961, 1962/63, 1963/64. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1964/65, 1965/66, 1968/69. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1969/70, 1970/71. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1972/73, 1973/74. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Related Landscape Publications
  - Agriculture and Energy (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The Journal of the New Alchemists, 1977. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- 1986 Additions
  - A Brochures, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Brochures (folder 2) Board meetings, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Board of Directors (continued), n.d. (Box 12)
  - Bulletin - chapters - Los Angeles, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Chapters (New England) - Convention, 1970 n.d. (Box 14)
  - Conventions, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Convention - competition, n.d. (Box 16)
  - I - Mail list, n.d. (Box 18)
  - D - H (contains History of AILA file), n.d. (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous - Photographs, n.d. (Box 19)
  - R - Z files, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Records books and financial data (Box 21, Box 22, Box 23)
  - Membership files, n.d. (Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34)
  - File drawer - records, n.d. (Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40)
  - Contents of cardboard box, n.d. (Box 41, Box 42, Box 43, Box 44)
  - ASLA records, contents of cardboard box, n.d. (Box 45, Box 46, Box 47)
  - Nursery catalogs, n.d. (Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51)
  - CCLA, n.d. (Box 52, Box 53)
  - CCLA files, n.d. (Box 56, Box 57, Box 58, Box 59, Box 60, Box 61, Box 62, Box 63)
  - AILA miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 54, Box 55)
  - ASLA material, early 1970s, n.d. (Box 64)
  - CCLA, ASLA, n.d. (Box 65)
  - Board of Directors, AILA journal, Landscape forum, etc. (Box 66)
  - Check stubs, n.d. (Box 67)
    [Inactive mold].
  - Membership files, alphabetical, n.d. (Box 68, Box 69, Box 70, Box 71, Box 72, Box 73, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76, Box 77, Box 78, Box 79, Box 80, Box 81, Box 82)
    Physical condition good; lengthy files in good alphabetical ìorder; correspondence, membership items, receipts, etc. Remove staples, paper clips; give folder level listing (33 folders per box equals 495 folders).
  - Chronological files, provenance unknown, ca. 1980-81.; Chronological files of Robert Cardoza as international president. Box 85 re ASLA/AILA unification; also few items in Box 84. Box 85 needs foldering; slight foldering needed 83-4. (Box 83, Box 84, Box 85)
  - Office files, topics and business, provenance unknown, 1979-80.; Same as previous, only some files have different color coding, ìalthough same type label. Provenance is probably the same. Provenance is Robert Cardoza as vice president of AILA. Box 87 includes some F.J. MacDonald as vice president materials. (Box 86, Box 87, Box 88, Box 89, Box 90)
  - Office files, provenance unknown, 1964-77. (Box 91, Box 92, Box 93)
    Provenance is secretary-treasurer, including membership files.
  - Office files, AILA northern chapter, n.d. (Box 94)
    [Provenance Andy Gotzenberg].
  - Design competition photographs and correspondence, 1977/78-81.; Contents from ring notebooks. Photocopies of correspondence and judges' remarks. Slides and photographs in deteriorating non-archival sleeves.. (Box 95, Box 96, Box 97, Box 98)
  - Publications, rosters, etc., 1970s-80s. (Box 99)
    DL recognizes most of these publications; most would seem to be duplicates, although they should be checked, of course.
  - Office files and publications, provenance unknown, ca.1970s. (Box 100, Box 101)
    Formed a separate filing/packing unit, although some folder titles are similar to previous ones. Provenance is Robert Cardoza.
  - Office files, provenance unknown, ca.1950s-60s. (Box 102)
    Records in older, deteriorating folders; provenance not given. These would seem to need the most descriptive attention.
  - See previous package 1, n.d. (Box 104)
  - Unlisted, n.d. (Box 103)
  - Additions March 1991 (unlisted), n.d. (Box 105, Box 106)